Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is י"א, Yud Alef,
שבועות Shevuot 11, and we pick up at the very top of
י"א, Yud Alef, עמוד א', Amud Alef, first line, אלא מעתה, Ela
me'ata, and we are dealing with the statement that עולא Ulla said
in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, that when you have
the תמידים, tmidim, that they would have four that would be set
aside that always available to bring from, and then it became the
time for the new year and then you would have leftover, that
you could be redeem them even without a blemish. And we're going
to see the even though of course you can never redeem a
sacrifice without a blemish and that was challenged, קדושה שבהן להיכן הלכה.
Keddusha she-hen l'heichan halcha. We will see, not to spoil the end,
but we will see that the גמרא Gemara is going to say
that the reason is לב בית דין מתנה עליהם. Lev Beis Din
masneh aleihem. Since they are sanctified by the ציבור tzibbur and by
the money that was gathered for the תרומה, terumah, for the קרבנות,
korbanot, and there was always known that there were going to be
leftover, so it was always implicitly stipulated that they would be able
to redeem it. And we'll see more about that later, but anyway
but that was because it was ציבור tzibbur and it was stipulated,
it was understood that would be the case. That's the reason we're
going to give. But right now that's being challenged about how can
you just make the קדושה keddusha disappear if you can't redeem a
קדושה keddusha without a קרבן korban without a blemish. And the proof
that you could do something like this that was brought was from
the קטורת, ktores, that you, and the קטורת ktores by the way
is similar in the fact that you would make the קטורת ktores
at the beginning of the year and you'd make a ton of
it, and by the time you got to the end of the
year you would have leftover and there would be a whole way
that you would redeem it even though קטורת ktores also presumably has
קדושת הגוף. keddushat haguf. You grind it in the grinder and that
was assumed to be a כלי שרת, kli shareis, and when it's
put into a כלי שרת kli shareis it becomes considered fit to
be offered up, and now it's ground and it's fit to be
offered up, and that should be קדושת הגוף keddushat haguf and nevertheless
you are able to redeem it. So you see, he said, that
you are able to do it, I'm making the claim by תמידים,
tmidim, but we already see that principle by the קטורת. ktores. And
the response back was, and just to I guess go to the
last line of י"א, עמוד ב', Yud Aleph Amud Bet. אמר ליה
קטורת קאמרת שאני קטורת דקדושת דמים היא. Amar lei ktores kamarta shaani
ktores d'keddushat damim hi. No, קטורת ktores is different, קטורת ktores only
has its only sanctified for its valuation until it really becomes fit
or put into a כלי שרת. kli shareis. And the way רש"י
Rashi explains it that this response assumed that the
מכתשת, makhteshet, the mortar and pestle, the thing that you would grind
it with was not a כלי שרת. kli shareis. So therefore even
though you sanctified it with your words, it has not yet been
sanctified to be seen as now at the stage of ready to
be offered up and therefore that's why it can be redeemed because
anything that just has קדושת דמים, keddushat damim, that is sanctified just
for its valuation, you automatically redeem it. It's not about a blemish,
it's not about being fit to be used. Okay, so that was
his answer. So now we pick up from י"א, Yud Alef, עמוד
א' Amud Alef whether it is really possible to dismiss קטורת ktores
as another good example of something that קדושת הגוף keddushat haguf that
you could redeem without a blemish, without a problem. אלא מעתה Ela
me'ata says the גמרא, Gemara, if you really think that it's קדושת
דמים keddushat damim even after it's been ground, לא תיפסל בטבול יום.
lo tipasel b'tvul yom. Then why why is it פסול pasul if
somebody is a טבול יום? tvul yom? Somebody is a טבול יום
tvul yom means they're טמא, tameh, they go to the מקוה, mikveh,
and it
says ובא השמש וטהר. uva hashemesh v'taher. When the sun sets you
become totally pure. So what is your state there after having gone
to the מקוה mikveh before the sun has set? That's a טבול
יום, tvul yom, somebody who immersed this day. And that status is
that of a effectively a שני לטומאה sheini l'tumah and somebody that
can make something that is קדש, kodesh, can make it פסול. pasul.
Okay, but only something that is קדוש קדושת הגוף. kadosh keddushat haguf.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara says if you're claim it's only
קדושת דמים, keddushat damim, why can a טבול יום tvul yom make
the קטורת ktores פסול? pasul? How do you know that he can
do that? אלמא תניא, Almah tanya, why did we teach in a
ברייתא, braita, ניטל ממכתשת ונפסלת בטבול יום. nittal m'makhteshet v'nifseles b'tvul yom.
Once you put the קטורת ktores into the pounder, into the mortar
and pestle,
now טבול יום tvul yom can make it פסול. pasul. Okay, so
you see it's קדושת הגוף keddushat haguf even as soon as it's
been ground, even before that is a כלי שרת, kli shareis, even
before it goes into any other כלי שרת. kli shareis. Now the
גמרא Gemara is going to say how how do I know what
how do you know this is correct that there can only a
טבול יום tvul yom can only work on a קדושת הגוף keddushat
haguf and not on a קדושת דמים? keddushat damim? וכי תימא כל
קדושת דמים מיפסלי
בטבול יום. Vechi teima kol keddushat damim mipseli b'tvul yom. You'll try
to deny my claim and you'll say that no even קדושת דמים,
keddushat damim, once it's קדוש kadosh it can become טמא tameh with
a טבול יום. tvul yom. You can't say that, דתנן, de-tnan, we
taught in מעילה, Me'ilah, המנחות מועלין בהן משיקדשו. ha-minchot moalin bahen misheyukdashu.
You know a מנחה, mincha, I mean and this lists all the
types of מעילה Me'ilah and all the different types of things you
bring to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, as soon as you sanctify
it you can do מעילה, Me'ilah, meaning if you do מעילה Me'ilah
you transgress, if you misuse it for your own purposes. משיקדשו. Misheyukdashu.
Okay, I put the comment there.
As soon as you sanctify them verbally, now there can be מעילה.
Me'ilah. קידשו בכלי, Kidshu bikeli,
once however you put them into a כלי שרת, kli shares, now
that sanctity becomes קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, now it's considered to be
fit for being offered up. קידשו בכלי הוכשרו ליפסל בטבול יום ובמחוסר
כיפורים ובלינה. Kidshu bikeli huchsharu lipasel bitvul yom uvimechusar kipurim uvilina.
Now if a טבול יום tvul yom touches it it becomes invalid,
or somebody who is a מחוסר כיפורים, mechusar kipurim, somebody who has
to bring a קרבן korban to finish their טהרה taharah process, like
a woman who gave birth or a זב zav or a מצורע,
metzora, they also have a residual טומאה tumah until they bring their
קרבן. korban. And לינה, lina, if it sleeps overnight, once it's fit
to be brought, if it stays overnight then it is also פסול.
pasul. So what do we see though? Something that clearly was קדוש,
kadosh, and you verbally sanctified the מנחה, mincha, and nevertheless it cannot
become פסול pasul with a טבול יום tvul yom until it is
sanctified with a כלי, keli, until it gets קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf.
Okay, so clearly פסול psul with a טבול יום tvul yom is
a indicator that this has קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. And that happens
with the קטורת ktoret once it is put in the מכתשת, machteshet,
the grinder, the mortar and the pestle. So you see it has
קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, and nevertheless you can redeem
it at the end of the year. So once again you see
the things that by the time it's the end of the year
and the things that were bought with the תרומה, trumah, with the
annual תרומה trumah of the חצי השקל chatzi hashekel and so on,
and that were bought by ציבור tzibur funds, those things it was
always implicitly stipulated could be redeemed at the end of the year
even though they had קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. Okay, so that was
a good support from קטורת ktoret and we see קטורת ktoret did
have קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf and nevertheless can be redeemed. But the
גמרא Gemara is not done. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אלא מאי, Ela mai, says the גמרא. Gemara. So what are you
trying to claim?
I skipped a line. לינה, קידשו בכלי אין, לא קידשו בכלי לא.
Lina, kidshu bikeli in, lo kidshu bikeli lo. So you see only
because it was sanctified in the vessel can it become פסול pasul
with the טבול יום tvul yom and not if it had not.
So you see that it does require קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, something
requires קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf to become פסול pasul with the טבול
יום, tvul yom, and that shows you that the קטורת ktoret once
it was put in the מכתשת machteshet does have קדושת הגוף kedushas
haguf because that's when it can become פסול pasul with the טבול
יום tvul yom and nevertheless it can be redeemed at the end
of the year. So now the גמרא Gemara says, אלא מאי, ela
mai, so what are you saying? What's your claim? קדושת הגוף? kedushas
haguf? You want to say that this קטורת ktoret has קדושת הגוף?
kedushas haguf? אלא מעתה תיפסל בלינה. Ela me'ata tipasel bilina. So look
at what we said by the case of the מנחה. mincha. By
the case of the מנחה mincha we said once it's put in
a כלי, keli, so now it can become פסול pasul with a
טבול יום, tvul yom, good, but we also said that once it
has קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, if it stays overnight it can become
פסול pasul with לינה, lina, right, you have to bring it that
day. Okay, if that's true, says the גמרא, Gemara, the same should
be true about the קטורת, ktoret, that the קטורת ktoret should be
פסול pasul with לינה lina as soon as you put it in
the מכתשת, machteshet, if that's your claim that it has קדושת הגוף.
kedushas haguf. But we know that's not true. אלמה תנן, Alama tnan,
why do we teach in a משנה mishna and this is the
same משנה mishna over there in מעילה, Me'ilah, very similar structure to
that of the מנחה mincha and it says the following. הקומץ, Hakometz,
the handbreadth that you would take from the מנחה, mincha, והלבונה, vehalivonah,
and the frankincense from the מנחה, mincha, והקטורת, vehaktoret, and that's our
friend the קטורת, ktoret, ומנחת כוהנים, uminchas kohanim, and the מנחה mincha
that
a כוהן kohein would bring would all be burned, ומנחת כוהן משיח,
uminchas kohein mashiach, and the מנחה mincha that the כוהן גדול kohein
gadol would bring every day, half in the morning and half in
the evening, ומנחת נסכים, uminchas nesachim, and the מנחה mincha that would
be brought with
every like a קרבן korban with an עולה olah and so on.
All of these things are things that would be fully burned. And
that's why they're in a separate משנה mishna from the מנחה mincha
because a מנחה mincha something would be offered and the rest would
be eaten and that has different הלכות halachos when it comes to
פיגול. pigul. Okay, but for us it doesn't really matter. Here's a
whole list of things that would be sanctified and what does it
say? It's just like it said by the
מנחה. mincha. מועלין בהם משהוקדשו, Mo'alin bahem mishekudshu, מעילה Me'ilah applies as
soon as they were verbally
sanctified. קידשו בכלי, Kidshu bikeli, once they were sanctified then they were
sanctified in a vessel,
הוכשרו ליפסל בטבול יום ובמחוסר כיפורים ובלינה. huchsharu lipasel bitvul yom uvimechusar
kipurim uvilina. Then they become now it becomes פסול pasul with a
טבול יום tvul yom and מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kipurim somebody waiting for
their sacrifices and with לינה lina sleeping overnight. So you see, says
the גמרא, Gemara, once it has this קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf it's
פסול pasul with לינה. lina. So what you really have here is
before we get to קדושת דמים kedushas damim and קדושת הגוף, kedushas
haguf, is you really have to reconcile this ברייתא braisa and the
משנה mishna because they seem to be saying different things. The ברייתא
braisa says that it
automatically is what do you call it that it automatically is
פסול pasul
can be פסול pasul with the טבול יום tvul yom as soon
as it's put into the מכתשת. machteshet. But it doesn't And then
can לינה *lina*. So that seems to say the מכתשת *machteshet* is
the כלי שרת *kli sharet*, and that's why it's פסול *pasul* with
טבול יום *tvul yom*. But for some reason לינה *lina* was left
off. This משנה mishnah *Mishna* says once it's put in a כלי
*kli*, now it's פסול *pasul* with טבול יום *tvul yom* and with
לינה *lina*. So the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* assuming that that כלי *kli* is
not the מכתשת *machteshet*. It's after it's been ground and now it's
put in the כלי *kli* ready to be offered. Okay, that's the
assumption, okay? And that's why that משנה mishnah *Mishna* adds the words
לינה *lina*. You have to assume that טבול יום *tvul yom* was
לאו דוקא *lav davka*, that was because there was a lot of
other things that were mentioned there that all got bundled together. But
now we've got this problem. One משנה mishnah *Mishna* says, the ברייתא
baraisa. *Baraita* seems to say that the קטורת ketoret *ktoret* is פסול
*pasul* with טבול יום *tvul yom* from the time it's ground, and
that that seems to be קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf *kdushat haguf*. And
this other משנה Mishnah: *Mishna* says only when it was put into
a later vessel does it now can become פסול *pasul* with לינה
*lina*. How do you explain this? At which moment does it become
קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf, *kdushat haguf*? How are these two things separated?
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* answers. אמר ליה
*Amar lei*, so he said back to him, לינה קאמרת *Lina kaamart*?
Wait, you're talking about לינה *lina*? שאני קטורת ketores הואיל וצורתה בכל
השנה כולה *Shani ktoret hoil v'tzurata b'chol hashana kula*. No, no, no.
קטורת ketores *Ktoret* has a special הלכה halacha *halacha* and the לינה
*lina* doesn't start from the moment it has קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf
*kdushat haguf*. Why? Because it keeps its appearance the entire year. Now
what does this mean? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says what this means
is there's no לינה *lina* at all by the קטורת Ketoret *ktoret*.
You know, קטורת ketores *ktoret* is fresh all year round and therefore,
it's an interesting idea, the concept of לינה *lina* only applies to
things that, you know, somehow like they get stale overnight or a
little stale, something starts happening to them. You know, but if the
קטורת ketoret *ktoret*, which is as good as it is a year
later, לינה'ס *lina's* not a relevant concept. That's the way רש"י Rashi,
*Rashi* explains. So it is קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf. *kdushat haguf* from
the time it's in the מכתשת *machteshet*. And this משנה Mishnah. *Mishna*
that said לינה *lina* when it puts in the next vessel, that's
דרבנן *derabanan*. But really there's no לינה *lina* and really it's full
קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf, *kdushat haguf* from the time of the מכתשת
*machteshet*. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* has a much better interpretation. Not that there's
no לינה *lina* at all. But תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* says because it
is made at the beginning of the year and it lasts the
whole year, the clock for לינה *lina* does not begin when it
is put in the כלי שרת *kli sharet*, the first כלי שרת
*kli sharet* of the מכתשת *machteshet*. Because it's always understood that you're
going to be compounding the whole amount and that it's not going
to be ready to be offered up, you know, you're doing the
whole amount for the whole year. And therefore it only becomes לינה
*lina* at the moment when it moves not just from קדושת הגוף
Kedushat Haguf. *kdushat haguf*, but קדושת הגוף Kedushat Haguf *kdushat haguf* that's
at the cusp of being offered up. And it's put in the
vessel from which it is going to be offered up. That's a
much better explanation. So because the קטורת *ktoret* is made for the
whole year, לינה *lina* comes at the next stage, not just קדושת
הגוף Kedushat Haguf. *kdushat haguf*, but קדושת הגוף Kedushat Haguf, *kdushat haguf*
in a כלי *kli* that it's ready to be offered up. All
right, so that's a nice answer. So now we're back to the
idea that the קטורת *ktoret* is קדושת הגוף Kedushat Haguf *kdushat haguf*
from the time it was ground. It was ground at the beginning
of the year and nevertheless you can redeem it. So we see
that it is a good example that is just like the תמידים
temidim *tmidim*, that it is something bought by the ציבור Tzibbur *tzibur*
with קדושת הגוף Kedushat Haguf *kdushat haguf* that can be redeemed at
the end of the year even though there is no blemish. So
that is a good proof to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan*.
But now we have to understand what is the logic behind it.
מכל מקום קשיא *Mikol makom kashya*, so okay, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says fine, you've proved that קטורת *ktoret* is just like what you're
saying about the תמידים temidim, *tmidim*. But it's still difficult to understand
this. וכי קדושה Kedusha שבהם להיכן הלכה *V'chi kdusha shebahem l'heichan halcha*?
How do you explain that you can just make the קדושה *kdusha*
go away without a blemish once it has קדושת הגוף Kedushat Haguf,
*kdushat haguf*? אמר רבה *Amar Rabba*, so now we finally get the
explanation for it, which I've been giving you in advance. לב בית
דין מתנה עליהם Lev Beis Din Masneh Aleihem. *Lev beit din matneh
aleihem*. The בית דין beit din *beit din*, you know, the body
that represents the Jewish people that buys the stuff with the funds
that have been gathered, okay, you know, they implicitly stipulate because they
understand, you know, there's going to be leftover at the end of
the year. And אם הוצרכו הוצרכו hutzrechu hutzrechu, *im hutzrechu hutzrechu*, what
we are buying with these funds of the תרומה *truma*, you know,
if it is going to be, if the things we are buying
are needed to be used on the מזבח mizbeach? *mizbeach*, then good,
then we are buying them and they have קדושת הגוף Kedushat Haguf
*kdushat haguf*. ואם לאו יהיו דמיהם *V'im lav yehiyu dmeihem*, but if
it turns out that we're that, you know, this particular amount of
קטורת *ktoret*, you know, we're buying a hundred pounds of קטורת *ktoret*
for the year, anything that's not used or any of those extra
animals that aren't used, if it turns out they won't be used
then when we are using הקדש *hekdesh* funds to buy them, we
don't want them to be sanctified קדושת הגוף Kedushat Haguf, *kdushat haguf*,
we only want them to be sanctified קדושת דמים kedushat damim, *kdushat
damim*. So at the end of the year you have leftover קטורת
*ktoret* or you have leftover animals, and then it turns out because
when we implicitly the initial stipulation, these were never sanctified as קרבנות,
korbanos they were only sanctified in terms of their valuation, and therefore
you can redeem it just like you can redeem something if somebody
sanctifies a car. Turns it in, it gets clarified that it was
always just to do just דמים damim for this stuff that got
left over. All right, that’s the nice background explanation, it makes a
lot of sense. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, Abaye said to
רבא, Rava, והא מר הוא דאמר, ve-ha mar hu de-amar, didn’t the
master say: הקדיש זכר לדמיו קדוש קדושת הגוף, hikdish zachar lidamav kadosh
kedushat haguf, that even if you try to sanctify something just for
its valuation in קדושת דמים, kedushat damim if it can be used
for a קרבן, korban, it will immediately get upgraded. So you take
a nice male unblemished animal and you
sanctify it for קדושת דמים kedushat damim. for the proceeds to be
used by the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. But this animal can be
an עולה, olah, and therefore, so it’s sanctified for its valuation,
but it could be used itself, so it automatically becomes קדושת הגוף
and now becomes a sanctity of an עולה. olah. So if that’s
true, then here too, even if the בית דין beit din is
saying that the קטורת or the תמידים Tmidim, are only קדושת הגוף,
they should automatically get upgraded. So how can this work? How can
the קדושת הגוף stay once
it adheres in an object that can be used itself for the
מזבח? Mizbeiach So the גמרא Gemara says: לא קשיא, lo kashya, that’s
not difficult. הא דאמר לדמי עולה והא דאמר לדמי נסכים. ha de-amar
lidmei olah ve-ha de-amar lidmei nesachim. It doesn’t automatically get upgraded, it
depends what purpose you had sanctified it for קדושת דמים. kedushat damim
If you took this nice sheep here, this male sheep, and you
said, I am sanctifying this sheep that its proceeds should be sold
and the proceeds should be used for an עולה. olah. Since the
קדושת דמים kedushat damim. is earmarked for an עולה, olah, why should
we wait, sell it and then buy an animal and have that
animal sanctified as an עולה? olah? Just eliminate the middleman, it automatically
becomes an עולה. olah. But if you say, I am sanctifying this
sheep and its proceeds should be used
for repairing the leak in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash or its
proceeds should be used for bringing wine offerings or anything else, then
that’s what the proceeds should be used for and it doesn’t become
an עולה. olah. It’s earmarked for something else. Now, he doesn’t explain
what if you don’t explicitly earmark it, you just say קדושת דמים.
kedushat damim Maybe that too would be considered to be automatically an
עולה. olah. But if it’s clearly earmarked for something else, it doesn’t
get
upgraded just because it adheres in an animal that could be used
for an עולה. olah. So here too as well, בית דין beit
din, would basically say, we’re sanctifying these sheep for קדושת הגוף. If
it turns out they’re not needed, it’s קדושת דמים kedushat damim for
and then something specifically else, and then it would be what they
use extra funds from the תרומת הלשכה terumat halishka for, they use
it for other types of repairs of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
So no, it would not get upgraded because implicitly they are saying
if it’s not needed, it’s קדושת דמים kedushat damim and קדושת דמים
kedushas damim, for some type of בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash repairs and
therefore it can be redeemed without a blemish. Okay. איתיביה אביי, Eitivei
Abaye, Abaye is still not happy. פרו ושעיר של יום הכיפורים שאבדו.
Paro ve-se'ir shel Yom HaKippurim she-avedu. Here we’ve got a משנה says
that if you have the cow or the goat of יום כיפור
Yom Kippur that got lost, the ones that are going to be
brought like in the inside of the קודש הקודשים, Kodesh HaKodashim, והפריש
אחרים תחתיהם, ve-hifrish acherim tachteihem, and you separated others in their place,
and then eventually you found the ones that were lost. Top here
of י"א Yud Alef, עמוד ב'. Amud Beis, וכן שעירי עבודה זרה,
Ve-chen se'irei avodah zarah,
or goats that were brought when the entire community worships עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, based on a פסק psak of a בית דין, beis
din שאבדו, she-avedu, and that they were lost, והפריש אחרים תחתיהם, ve-hifrish
acherim tachteihem, and then you brought others in their place. And then
you found the original ones. What are you going to do with
it? כולן ימותו. Kullan yamutu. You can’t use it, so you gotta
let them die. דברי רבי יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yehuda. That’s what רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. Now, why can’t you use it? In our
משנה we saw that if you can’t use something, the goats of
one for like the מוסף musaf of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you
can use it
for the רגלים regalim or for ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh etc. So
רש"י Rashi says, well because here the only thing you could use
for those
were next יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and by next יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, because these here were like the things that were not like
those cases in the משנה that they could not be,
since these were brought on the inside of the קודש הקודשים, Kodesh
HaKodashim, they can't be used for the other types of things on
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh or whatever. They could only be used for
next יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and by then, says רש"י, Rashi a
year will have passed and they won’t be the right age. So
therefore they couldn’t be used.
Now תוספות Tosafot says... Whoops, I
actually, excuse me, I misstated that. It's not that they wouldn't be
the right age, it's not, but that the problem here would be,
would be that you have to again bring them from this year's,
you know, funds. That's what רש"י Rashi says the problem is. You
have to wait till next year and they would have been bought
with last year's funds. Yeah, the age would not have been a
problem. תוספות Tosafot says no, that's not true, that's only לכתחילה, lechatchila,
it's not בדיעבד. bedieved. The problem would be that if we can't
wait a year because if we wait a year, they might come
to be misused and we won't allow you to wait a year
and have them sit around that long. Okay, but one way or
the other, the point is is that we're not going to use
them next יום כיפור Yom Kippur and what are you going to
do with them? So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you gotta let
them die. The general principle is a חטאת chatas that cannot be
used, חטאת שכיפרו בעליה באחר, chatas shekapru be'alav be'acher, that, you know,
where another one was used and then these were found, and this
can't be used for its original designation, you have to let die.
That's the general הלכה by חטאת מתה. chatas meisos.
So he says it's no different here even though it's a ציבור
חטאת. tzibbur chatas. רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Elazar v'Rabbi Shimon
omer, but רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say,
ירעו עד שיסתאבו וימכרו ויפלו דמיהן לנדבה. yiru ad sheyistavu veyimkaru veyiplu
demeihem l'nedava. No, no, no. These you can actually redeem. You let
them graze until they get a blemish and then you redeem them
and then you use the money to bring as an עולה, olah,
okay? That's the—so it's like—it is like other קרבנות korbanos that you
can redeem.
Now, שאין חטאת ציבור מתה, sheein chatas tzibbur meisa, because that principle
that you let a חטאת chatas die is only by a חטאת
chatas of a יחיד, yachid, but a חטאת ציבור chatas tzibbur you
don't let die. The principle is that once it gets a blemish
you're allowed to redeem it and use its money for an עולה.
olah. Okay. Now why is this relevant for us? So the גמרא
Gemara says ואמאי, v'amai, why do you have to wait for it
to have a blemish
according to רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar and רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? And
why do you have to let it die according to רבי יהודה?
Rabbi Yehuda? This is a communal קרבן, korban, so לימא לב בית
דין מתנה עליהן. leima lev beis din masneh aleihem. Why not say
that, you know, implicitly when anything is bought with communal funds, the
בית דין beis din should stipulate that if they don't get, you
know, הוצרכו הוצרכו,
if it gets used for the right thing great, and if it
doesn't get wind up getting used for the right thing, it's not
קדושת הגוף, it's only קדושת דמים, Kedushat Damim. right? If you say
it by the קטורת and the תמידים, temidim, why not say it
here? And the answer's pretty obvious. אבודים קאמרת—wait, avudim kamartah if something
got lost? You want to apply what we were saying before to
this case of something got lost? That's a special case. שאני אבודים
דלא שכיחי. shani avudim d'lo shechichi. That's not a common occurrence. רש"י
also says the קרבנות aren't common. Okay? So therefore you can't—it's not
relevant. Because when you buy the קטורת at the beginning of the
year, you know that there's going to be leftover. When you're buying
regularly having, you know, you know, these animals in the לשכת הגזית,
Lishkas HaGazis, okay, that I mean say you'd have six and then
you take two and then four would be left each time, whatever,
and you'd have four left over, right? So you know that there
are going to be four left. Okay? So therefore we stipulated from
the very outset. This is a freak occurrence and we don't make
that type of a stipulation. We're not anticipating it, we don't want
that, you know, whatever, we're not making it every single time. We're
making it for the standard needs.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute. Okay, that seems
like a really good answer. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. והרי פרה דלא שכיחא—one v'harei parah d'lo shechicha minute. The פרה
אדומה parah adumah is an uncommon situation. Now, פרה אדומה parah adumah
itself is uncommon, that might be what the גמרא Gemara means, or
if there's a problem with the פרה אדומה parah adumah as we're
going to see. But let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay,
it's going to show a case of a פרה אדומה parah adumah
where it understands that it only operates because of this principle of
לב בית דין מתנה עליהן. lev beis din masneh aleihem. Otherwise you
wouldn't be able to redeem it. So it's going to say you
see בית דין Beis Din, does stipulate even by, like, infrequent cases,
not cases that could be normally anticipated. Let's take a look. Okay,
דלא שכיחי, d'lo shechichi, that's not common, ותניא—it's v'tanya taught in a
ברייתא. braisa, פרה נפדית על כל פסול שבה. parah nifdes al kol
psul shebah. They would redeem a פרה אדומה parah adumah if any
blemish was found, not you know any
problem. מתה—or meisa even if it died, תיפדה—it tipadeh could be redeemed.
Now that's a little, you know, interesting, I mean that's a big
blemish. Okay, so—but even if it died before it was שחט shechted
or whatever, it could be
redeemed. נשחטה—it nishchata was slaughtered, but not slaughtered on, you know, הר
המשחה, Har HaMishcha, you know, הר הזיתים, Har HaZeisim, it was slaughtered
in some other place that was not a כשר kosher place for
it to be slaughtered, תיפדה—you tipadeh could redeem it. Even מצא אחרת
נאה הימנה תיפדה. matza acheres na'ah himenu tipadeh. Even if you found
one that was more beautiful than it, you could redeem it. Okay,
so you could redeem it for any time you had a need.
עד ששחטה על גבי מערכתה—once, ad sheshachata agabbai maarachtah however, you slaughtered
it on the, like, you know, the pyre or whatever, you know,
the wood where you were going to burn it or whatever, in
the right place, then אין לה פדייה עולמית. ein lah pidyon olamis.
Then you could no longer redeem it because now it would be,
the way רש"י says, technically you could, but once everything was done
properly, it would be a גנאי, gnai, it would be demeaning to
be redeeming it once it had gotten to that stage. or whatever,
you wanted a nicer one. Okay, anyway, that's not relevant for us.
What's relevant is that you would redeem it even if you found
a nicer one, even without a blemish. So presumably the only way
to explain that is that it's קדושת דמים. Kedushat Damim? You know,
it's לב בית דין מתנה עליהם. Lev Beis Din Masneh Aleihem So
you see לב בית דין מתנה עליהם lev beis din masneh aleihem.
operates even in non-standard
cases. Good question. So the גמרא Gemara says no. שני פרה דקדשי
בדק הבית היא. Shani Parah Dekadshey Bedek Habayis Hi. פרה אדומה's Parah
Adumah different. It doesn't have קדושת הגוף. You know, פרה אדומה's Parah
Adumah a very strange animal, haha, because it's slaughtered outside of the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, facing the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but the
blood doesn't go, the blood is sprinkled towards the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash but not in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So is it
a קרבן? Korban? Is it a קדושת הגוף or is it a
קדושת דמים? Kedushat Damim. So the גמרא Gemara, says that it is
a קדושת דמים. Kedushat Damim. It never really has that, you know,
even you know that that sense that it's intrinsically קדוש Kadosh for
its use. Although it's pretty funny, it is being used, just not
used as a קרבן, Korban, so you would still think that's קדושת
הגוף. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara claims that פרה Parah has a,
this is a general position of the גמרא, Gemara that פרה אדומה
Parah Adumah is just קדושת דמים. Kedushat Damim. And that's why you
can redeem it and you don't need a blemish and so on.
You don't need לב בית דין מתנה. Lev Beis Din Masneh. Its
standard קדושה is קדושת דמים. Kedushat Damim So what are we saying?
When it comes to the קטורת and it comes to the תמידים,
temidim, okay, that would be, that's you can anticipate there's going to
be leftover, anything leftover was not intended to be קדושת הגוף, was
only intended to be קדושת דמים Kedushat Damim. and can be redeemed
without a blemish. Okay, but when you have some other ציבור thing
that was a freak case, like you know like a חטאת, Chatas,
you know like the פר Par on יום כיפור Yom Kippur got
lost or whatever, there's no stipulation. You just have to deal with
that as you would, let it die, let it get a blemish
and so on. פרה אדומה Parah Adumah you can redeem even though
that's not something like you know not something you normally anticipate and
it's an uncommon case, because that is only קדושת דמים. Kedushat Damim,
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. שני פרה דקדשי
בדק הבית היא.
Shani Parah Dekadshey Bedek
Habayis Hi. Okay, it's קודש קדשי בדק הבית. Kodesh Kadshey Bedek Habayis.
Now
I should actually say, I was saying קדושת דמים, Kedushat Damim, but
the גמרא Gemara, is actually more precise than that. You know, and
I think I said this on the previous דף. Daf. There's two
different
concepts: קדושת הגוף and קדושת דמים, Kedushat Damim which means קדושת הגוף
is the thing itself is going to be used and קדושת דמים
Kedushat Damim, is it's going to be sold and you're going to
get the proceeds. And then there's קדשי מזבח Kadshey Mizbeiach and קדשי
בדק הבית. Kadshey Bedek Habayis. It's going to be used on the
מזבח Mizbeiach, and it's going to be used for, you know,
for fixing up the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, now normally those
you would think that those are parallel. It's intrinsically sanctified, קדושת הגוף,
you're going to now bring it as a קרבן. Korban. You know,
it's you sanctified it for its proceeds, I sell the car you're
going to sell it and use the money to fix up the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. But they're not the same category. You could
have something that is קדושת הגוף but it is בדק הבית. Bedek
Habayis. It's intrinsically sanctified, but you're going to use it not for
a קרבן, Korban, but you're going to use it for other בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash purposes. I sanctified a beam that's going to be
built into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. That's קדושת הגוף לבדק הבית.
Kedushat Haguf LeBedek Habayis. Or the פרה Parah here is קדושת הגוף,
not קדושת דמים, you are using the פרה Parah itself, so you're
not selling it. But it is a קדושת הגוף לבדק הבית Kedushat
Haguf LeBedek Habayis for something other than a קרבן Korban purpose. Okay,
but since again it is not a קרבן, Korban, it can be
redeemed without a blemish. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. שני פרה דקדשי בדק הבית היא. Shani Parah Dekadshey Bedek Habayis
Hi. אי הכי, I hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara מתו נשחטה תיפדה?
Meiso nishchata tipadeh?
If that's true, how can you, if it's קדשי בדק הבית, Kadshey
Bedek Habayis, how can you redeem it once it's dead? Why not?
You know, הבעינן המעמד והערכה. Ha be'inan hama'amad veha'aracha. The תורה Torah
says when it speaks about sanctifying animals, you shall stand it before
the כהן Kohen and the כהן Kohen shall assess the value. And
there's a whole debate, does that apply to animals that are for
the מזבח, does it apply to animals that are for בדק הבית?
Bedek Habayis? So the גמרא Gemara here, it's not exactly clear why
the גמרא's Gemara making this assumption, but the גמרא Gemara here is
assuming that maybe the, that maybe if it was קדשי מזבח Kadshey
Mizbeiach who knows, maybe you could redeem it, we would understand once
it's dead you could redeem it. But now that you're saying it's
בדק הבית, Bedek Habayis, why can you redeem it if it's dead?
Don't they need to be alive to, in order to be redeemed?
So the גמרא Gemara says, הא מני רבי שמעון היא, Ha mani
Rabbi Shimon hi, דאמר קדשי מזבח היו בכלל המעמד והערכה קדשי בדק
הבית לא היו בכלל המעמד והערכה. De'amar Kadshey Mizbeiach hayu bechlal hama'amad
veha'aracha Kadshey Bedek Habayis lo hayu bechlal hama'amad veha'aracha. No, it's רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says if it were a
קרבן, Korban, then yes, it would have to be alive. But it
because it is, but something that is קדשי בדק הבית, Kadshey Bedek
Habayis, that can be redeemed. even if it's dead. So fits perfectly.
The פרה אדומה Parah Adumah is קדשי בדק הבית. kodshei bedek habayis.
That's why it could be redeemed even if you find something more
beautiful, it's not about בית דין, beis din it always was קדשי
בדק הבית, kodshei bedek habayis, and that's also why it can be
redeemed even if it's dead. So now the גמרא Gemara says אי
רבי שמעון ei Rabbi Shimon one minute, if it's רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the end. שחטה אגב
מערכתה אין לה פדיה עולמית. shachta agav ma'arachta ein la pedia olamis.
Okay,
if you שחט shechted it in the right place, you can't redeem
it once, once it's שחט shechted and everything was proper, now you're
already starting the מצוה, mitzvah, you now you can't redeem. So the
גמרא Gemara, says והתניא, ve-hatanya, but we learned in a ברייתא, braisa
רבי שמעון אומר פרה מטמאה טומאת אוכלין הואיל והיתה לה שעת הכושר,
Rabbi Shimon omer parah metamei tumas ochlin ho'il ve-haysa la sha'as hakosher,
that a פרה אדומה Parah Adumah is considered food because it had
a moment where it could be eaten. Now, what does that mean?
When it's alive it can't be eaten. Once it's שחט shechted even
שחט shechted in the right place, it's אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. Okay,
you can't benefit from a פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. So how could
it be considered food that it would be susceptible to the טומאה
tumah of foodstuff if something טמא tamei touched it? So the answer
is because there was a moment when it could be eaten. What
was that moment? After it was שחט, shechted, okay, since in theory
you could have redeemed it then, so even though it hadn't been
redeemed, since in theory you could be redeemed and then it was
שחט shechted properly, it could be eaten, that is enough to give
it the status of food that it could get טומאה tumah if
something touches it. Okay, we're not going to get into טומאה tumah
of food, but the point is is that he is saying implicit
in this statement is even after it's שחט shechted it can be
at least in theory redeemed. So how can you say that this
statement of פרה אדומה Parah Adumah that it lets it to be
allows it to be redeemed once it's dead, which we're saying was
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says קדשי בדק הבית kodshei bedek habayis
can be redeemed even if they're dead, how could that be consistent
with רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon if רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, if
the ברייתא braisa says that it can't be that it can't
be redeemed once it's שחט shechted and we know רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says that a פרה parah can be redeemed even after it's
שחט? shechted? So the גמרא Gemara says ואמר ריש לקיש אומר היה
רבי שמעון פרה נפדית על גב מערכתה. ve-amar Reish Lakish omer haya
Rabbi Shimon parah nifdis agav ma'arachta. Oh, I said that outside without
reading ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish explains what does
it mean that it had a שעת הכושר sha'as hakosher that in
theory could be eaten because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that you
could have redeemed it even after it was שחט. shechted. Okay, so
this ברייתא can't be רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So if it can't
be רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we're back to the question of why
can you redeem it even if the animal is dead, even if
it was only קדשי בדק הבית? kodshei bedek habayis?
So the גמרא, Gemara it needs העמדה והערכה. ha'amada ve-ha'aracha. So the
גמרא Gemara says fine, you're right. אלא שאני פרה הואיל ודמיה יקרין.
ela shani parah ho'il ve-dameha yekarin. Fine, you're right. The פרה אדומה
Parah Adumah is also something that לב בית דין מתנה עליהם. lev
beis din masneh aleihem, So why? Because since it was so expensive,
there was always an implicit understanding that the בית דין beis din,
would have that if there's any need, you could redeem it. You
know, it was a דווקא davka because it was a very rare
thing and they really wanted to make sure that everything went right,
they had an implicit stipulation that would like allow you to redeem
it. So now where are we? The קטורת and the תמידים, temidim,
you know there's going to be leftover, לב בית דין מתנה עליהם,
lev beis din masneh aleihem. you can redeem it without a blemish.
The פר par of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you know the שעיר
se'ir of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, even if something happens, no לב
בית דין מתנה עליהם. lev beis din masneh aleihem Freak occurrence, rare
case, whatever. Okay, you're stuck. פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, if something happens
and even if there was something more beautiful or whatever, okay, there
was a לב בית דין מתנה עליהם lev beitin matnai aleihem. that
basically made it possible to redeem and even if after the animal
died, somehow we got around that problem because it was all part
of the stipulation of בית דין, beis din and בית דין Beitin
sort of had a stipulation there because it was so
expensive and that they wanted to make sure there would always be
that out to make it possible to redeem. Now, I should say
I don't really understand the point of it being expensive because, okay,
it was expensive. You spent a hundred thousand dollars on this פרה.
parah. But now it's dead, right? And now you're going to redeem
it? Or I don't know, you found a more beautiful one. But
you're going to and so you'll sell the original one what, to
a farmer? Right, if you're not going to need it for the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it stops being דמיה יקרין. dameha yekarin. So
now there's another even more beautiful פרה אדומה Parah Adumah or this
one I don't know died and or had some problem with it
or whatever, it was שחט shechted in the wrong place, and now
you want to buy this other one, that's going to cost you
that other one another hundred thousand dollars. You're not recouping the hundred
thousand dollars you spent on this original one. So being allowed to
redeem it just allows you to salvage the cost of the actual
cow, of how much a normal... So I don't really understand how
דמי יקרים, demei yekarim, you know, mean that we should more stipulate
to make it easy to redeem. And anything else? Anyway, that's what
the גמרא Gemara says, I really can't understand that. We're going to
see something similar in the next line. So גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר מר: Amar Mar: מתה
תפדה, Metah tipadeh, if it died, you know, you didn't שחט shecht
it, it just died on you, you could redeem it. וכי פודים
את הקדשים להאכילם לכלבים? Vechi pofim et hakodshim leha'achilam laklavim? Can you
redeem something that's sanctified in order to feed it to the dogs?
You know, like what are you going to do with it? It's
a נבילה. neveilah. You know, all you could do is feed it
to the dogs. That's not respectful of it. תוספות has a whole
discussion: are we assuming now קדשי בדק הבית kodshei bedek habayit or
are we assuming קדשי מזבח? kodshei mizbeach? What are we assuming? Anyway,
we're not going to get into that. So the גמרא Gemara just
says: what are you going to do with it that you're going
to redeem it? So אמר רב משארשיא משום עורא. Amar Rav Mesharshiya
mishum ora. Yes, that because—well no, you're not going to feed the
meat to the dogs, but you'll be able to use the leather.
And that's why we—you're—we're allowing you to redeem it. So the גמרא
Gemara says: וקיימי בית דין ומתני אדעתא דעורא? Vekayami beitin umatnai ada'ata
de'ora? בית דין is going to make a whole stipulation just in
order to let you salvage the leather? Like, that's sort of my
point. Who cares how much the cow costs? What are you going
to salvage now? The leather? Big deal.
So—so the גמרא Gemara says: אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, yes,
עמי אינש דאיגמלה אונה. ami insh de'igamlah unah. If from a camel,
if I—you know, at least let me salvage the ear. Yes, this
thing was worth a lot, but I want to at least feel
like I salvaged something. So yes, they will מתנה matnai so you
can salvage something. So maybe that's what דמי יקרים demei yekarim means.
Since you spent all this money, you know, they want to at
least give you the opportunity to salvage something out of it because
you're going to feel really despondent if there was nothing you walked
away with. Maybe that's what it means. Okay. איתיבי. Eitvei. Now we're
going to see why we had this whole discussion here, but we
basically have concluded לב בית דין מתנה עליהם. lev beitin matnai aleihem?
You know, and certainly in regular cases like the קטורת and the
תמידים, and maybe also in the פרה אדומה parah adumah case because
it's a special case.
All right. אמרו
לו לרבי שמעון. Amru lo le-Rabbi Shimon. So the Rabbis said to
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in our משנה: מהו שיקרבו זה בזה? Ma'u
sheyakrivu zeh be-zeh? Can you bring a קרבן, korban, you know, of
the רגלים regalim for, you know, ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh or for
the מוסף Musaf of יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? You know, whatever, you
know, from—you know, for—for—you know, for the רגלים. regalim. So because each
one is doing a slightly different piece of טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. tumat
mikdash ve-kodashav.
So אמר להם—he amar lahem said back to them: יקרבו. Yikrevu. Yes,
you can. אמרו לו—they Amru lo said to him: הוין כפרתן שווה
היכן קריבין? Havein kaparatam shaveh heichan kreivin? They said: one minute. They're
not exactly the same. They're different elements of טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. tumat
mikdash ve-kodashav. How can you just use one for the other? אמר
להם—he Amar lahem said back to them: כולם באים לכפר על טומאת
מקדש וקדשיו. Kulam ba'in le-chaper al tumat mikdash ve-kodashav. Well, they're all
for טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tumat mikdash ve-kodashav, so that's similar enough so
you can use one for the other. Fine. That's our משנה. So
now the גמרא Gemara says: ואמאי לימא לב בית דין מתנה עליהם?
Ve-amai leima lev beitin matnai aleihem? Why did רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
need to give that reason? Why couldn't רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon have
said לב בית דין מתנה עליהם? lev beitin matnai aleihem, If you
can't use it for one, you know, why you can use it
for the other? Because like, since it was bought from communal funds,
there was always be an implicit stipulation, you know, that if something
happened, you could go ahead and like use it for the next
one. Now, of course, the funny thing is, this is just like
a case of something getting lost. Why would you use it? Because
it got lost, and now you want to use it again. So
we already said that לב בית דין מתנה עליהם, lev beitin matnai
aleihem you know, doesn't apply when it got lost. So תוספות says:
well, you know, maybe this is a more common קרבן, korban, the
earlier case was a rarer קרבן. korban. Not exactly clear why the
גמרא Gemara thinks לב בית דין מתנה עליהם lev beitin matnai aleihem,
applies here since we were more limiting the scope of לב בית
דין מתנה. lev beitin matnai. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says: why did
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon not be able to use that reason if
that's an existing reason? Now, you could say this is a better
reason. Fundamentally, you know, it's all in the same category. But let's
see what the גמרא says.
רבי שמעון קאמרת? Rabbi Shimon ka'amart? The גמרא says: wait, you're asking
me about רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? רבי שמעון לית ליה לב בית
דין מתנה עליהם. Rabbi Shimon leit lei lev beitin matnai aleihem. No,
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, we know elsewhere we're going to make an
argument, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon fundamentally doesn't agree with this whole point
that we've been saying. He rejects לב בית דין. lev beitin. How
do you know? דאמר רב אידי בר אבין אמר רב עמרם אמר
רבי יוחנן: De-amar Rav Idi bar Abin amar Rav Amram amar Rabbi
Yochanan: תמידים שלא הוצרכו לציבור. Temidim shelo hutzrechu le-tzibbur. The case we
started with in the name of רבי יוחנן, that the extra תמידים,
the four that were left over at the end of the year,
לדברי רבי שמעון אין נפדין תמימים ולדברי חכמים נפדין תמימים. le-divrei Rabbi
Shimon ein nifdin temimim u-le-divrei Chachamim nifdin temimim. Okay.
So for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, would say you're stuck with them,
you have to wait for them to be a blemish. It's only
the Rabbis who argue on רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, they hold לב
בית דין מתנה עליהם, they hold the principle we've been articulating this
entire דף, daf, which is that they can be redeemed even without
a blemish. Okay, and that is the debate of רבנן ורבי שמעון.
Rabbanan ve-Rabbi Shimon. We will see tomorrow where we get that this
is the debate between these two positions.